When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we explore the findings
of five massive new trials
of the effectiveness of
fish oil supplements.
Thanks in part to the
American Heart
Association's recommendation
that individuals at high risk
for heart disease
ask their physicians
about omega-3
fish oil supplementation,
fish oil pills have grown into
a multibillion-dollar industry.
We now consume more
than a hundred thousand tons
of fish oil every year.
But what does the science say?
Are the purported benefits
of fish oil supplementation
for the prevention and treatment
of heart disease promising,
or just a fish tale?
The scientific sea change
occurred a little over
a decade ago
when a systematic review
and meta-analysis
published in the Journal of
the American Medical Association
looked at all the best
randomized clinical trials
evaluating the effects
of omega-3 fats on life span,
cardiac death, sudden death,
heart attack, and stroke.
These included studies
not only on fish oil supplements
but also studies
on the effects
of advising people
to eat more oily fish.
Overall, the researchers found
no protective benefit
for overall mortality,
heart disease mortality,
sudden cardiac death,
heart attack, or stroke.
What about for someone who had
already had a heart attack
and is trying
to prevent another one?
Still no benefit was found.
Since then, another five-dozen
randomized, controlled trials
have been compiled,
and the most extensive
systematic assessment confirmed
that increasing the intake
of fish fats (EPA and DHA)
had "little or no effect
on deaths
and cardiovascular events."
Longevity experiments on mice
found no benefits for aging
or lifespan either.
Where did we even get this idea
that the omega-3 fats in fish
and fish oil supplements
were good for us?
There was a notion that Eskimos
were protected
from heart disease,
but that appears to be
a complete myth.
Some early studies,
however, looked promising.
For example,
the famous DART trial
from the 1980s
involving 2,000 men
found that those
advised to eat fatty fish
had a 29 percent reduction
in mortality.
That's impressive,
no wonder the study
got a lot of attention.
Fish oil
became a whale of a story
that got bigger
with every telling.
But people seem to have
forgotten about the sequel,
the DART-2 trial,
which found the exact opposite.
Run by the same group
of researchers,
the DART-2 trial
was an even bigger study,
3,000 men,
but this time,
participants advised
to eat oily fish
and particularly those
who were supplied
with fish oil capsules
had a higher risk
of cardiac death.
Concerns about the potential
pro-arrhythmic (irregular
rhythm inducing) effects
of fish oil has led to reviews
containing titles like,
"Can Fish Oil Kill You?"
But again, little or no change
in overall mortality risk
has been found when all
the studies are put together.
Beyond just concerns
about persistent pollutants,
such as dioxins and PCBs
in fish oil supplements,
even in "distilled"
fish oil supplements,
oxidation by-products
have been found
throughout the commercial
fish oil supplements industry.
Surveys of popular omega-3
supplements in Asia, Europe,
the Middle East,
Australia, and North America
found that 24-92 percent
exceeded the voluntary
safety standards
set by the industry,
there's no legal limit,
at least in the United States.
The country of origin
didn't seem to matter,
perhaps because
most fish oil products
sold globally
are evidently sourced
from the same region (off the
west coast of South America).
Surprisingly, the best-before
date also wasn't helpful.
In this study, where nine
out of ten supplements
exceeded safety standards,
they were all tested
at least nine months before
the best-before dates.
The more expensive ones
were more contaminated,
but this is thought to be
an artifact of higher cost
relating to
higher concentrations.
Those obtained from algae
were also better
than those from fish.
The United States has
the highest sales of fish oil
in the world,
exceeding a billion dollars
a year.
When three top-selling
fish oil supplements
in the U.S. were tested,
they all exceeded
the recommended maximum levels
of oxidation products,
though expanded testing
to four dozen U.S. supplements
only found 52 percent
exceeded the limits.
And these two tests
may give false positives
due to added colors or flavors.
A USDA study found
that more than 70 percent
contained less EPA and/or DHA
than stated on their labels,
but the greater concern
is not what fish oil supplements
are lacking
but rather what's not listed
on the label,
like the contaminants,
oxidation by-products,
and saturated fat,
which may explain
why fish-based omega-3s
raise LDL cholesterol levels
compared to
plant-based omega-3s.
The public health implications
of consuming oxidized fish oil
are unclear, however.
Animal experiments
suggest chronic exposure
can cause inflammation,
organ toxicity,
and accelerated atherosclerosis,
but no long-term human studies
have been done.
Ironically, one of the reasons
there haven't been
more clinical studies
are the ethical concerns
knowingly exposing people
to oxidized fats;
yet, that experiment
is being carried out en masse
as we speak
in bathroom medicine cabinets
around the world.
After putting
all the studies together,
the authors of the landmark
AMA journal meta-analysis
concluded that there was
no longer justification
for the use of omega-3s
in everyday clinical practice.
What should doctors do
when their patients follow
the American
Heart Association's advice
and inquire
about fish oil supplements?
As the director
of Lipids and Metabolism
at Mount Sinai's
Cardiovascular Institute put it:
"Given this and other
negative meta-analyses,
our job as doctors
should be to stop
highly marketed
fish oil supplementation
to all our patients."
The research momentum was
already in full swing, though,
and five massive new trials
have been recently published
randomizing tens of thousands
to various formulations
of fish oil versus placebo.
Four out of five flopped.
The so-called ASCEND trial,
the OMEMI trial,
the STRENGTH trial,
and the VITAL trial
all failed to reduce deaths
or cardiovascular events,
but one final nail
in the coffin
appeared to be loose.
The REDUCE-IT trial
didn't significantly reduce
overall mortality
but did reduce a composite
of cardiovascular events
by 25 percent.
It used
a prescription-only dose of EPA,
equivalent to eating about
150 cans of tuna fish a day.
The problem
is the placebo they used.
Unlike other trials that used
more neutral oils like corn oil,
the drug company
that funded REDUCE-IT
to promote its own product
chose mineral oil
for the control group,
a classic drug industry trick
where you try to make
your product look better
by comparing it
against something worse.
And, indeed the mineral oil
quote-unquote "placebo"
increased LDL cholesterol
and caused more than
a 30 percent increase
in C-reactive protein.
No wonder the fish oil
looked good in comparison.
It's possible some fish oil
formulation will eventually
prove to be helpful,
but for now, meta-analyses
"unequivocally demonstrate
that there is no
cardiovascular benefit"
to over-the-counter
fish oil supplements.
In our next story,
we look at how a study of 13 over-the-counter
children’s fish oil supplements
found that all were contaminated
with PCB pollutants.
A number of so-called case-control
studies like this one
have found that giving kids
cod liver oil supplements
may increase their risk
of asthma later in life.
Case-control studies are done
by asking about past behavior
in cases (those with asthma) versus
controls (those without asthma)
to see if certain past behaviors are
more common among the disease group.
The problem is you’re asking people to
remember what they were doing years ago,
and most people can’t remember what
they had for breakfast last week,
and you can’t rule out something
called reverse causation.
Maybe cod liver oil
didn’t lead to the asthma,
maybe the asthma led to
the use of cod liver oil.
So it would be nice
to see a cohort study.
You take people without
asthma at the beginning
and you see if those that you
know are taking cod liver oil
are more likely to develop it.
That gets around the problems of
recall bias and reverse causation.
And here it is.
17,000 people free of asthma, we know
who's taking cod liver oil and who isn't,
and then we see who gets
asthma over the next 11 years.
And they indeed found that
cod liver oil intake
was significantly associated
with the development of asthma.
They think it may be the
excessive vitamin A
in the cod liver oil that
was causing the problem,
but there are a number of things in fish oil
we may not want our children exposed to.
Researchers recently looked at 13
over-the-counter children’s dietary supplements
containing fish oil to assess
potential exposure to PCBs,
toxic industrial pollutants that
have contaminated our oceans.
PCBs were detected in ALL products.
Could you just stick to the supplements
made from the small, short-lived fish
like anchovies instead of big predator fish
like tuna, or use the purified fish oils?
No! They found no significant
difference in PCB levels
between the supplements labeled
as molecularly distilled
or however high up the
food chain the fish were.
So while children’s dietary
supplements containing
the long-chain omega-3’s from fish oils
may CLAIM to benefit young consumers,
daily ingestion of these products may
provide a vector for contaminant exposure
that may off-set the
positive health effects.
What positive health effects
are they talking about?
Well, infants given DHA-fortified
formula may have better development
of their eyes and brains compared to
infants getting non DHA-fortified formula.
DHAs are one these long-chain
omega-3 fatty acids.
But what was the
source of the DHA?
Not fish!
It was algae-derived DHA.
So you can get the benefits of
omega 3’s without the contaminant risks.
Of course, breast milk
is the gold standard,
significantly better than either
of the formula fed infants.
So the best source
of omega-3’s is mom.
Finally today,
we discover how advice to
eat oily fish, or take fish oil,
is no longer supported by the
balance of available evidence.
Are purported benefits of
fish oil supplementation
for the prevention and treatment
of heart disease
just a "fish tale"?
Thanks to recommendations
like this
from the American Heart Association,
that individuals at high
risk for heart disease
ask their physicians about
fish oil supplementation,
it's grown into a multi-
billion dollar industry.
We now consume over 100,000 tons
of fish oil every year.
But what does the
latest science say?
A systematic review and
meta-analysis published in
the Journal of the
American Medical Association
looked at all the best
randomized clinical trials
evaluating the effects
of omega-3s
on lifespan, cardiac death, sudden death,
heart attack, and stroke.
Either advice to eat
more oily fish
or to take
fish oil capsules.
What did they find?
Overall they found NO
protective benefit
for overall mortality,
heart disease mortality,
sudden cardiac death,
heart attack, or stroke.
What about for those who've already
had a heart attack, though,
and are trying to
prevent another one?
Still NO benefit.
Where did we even
get this idea
that omega-3s were
good for the heart?
Well, if you look at some
of the older studies,
the results
looked promising,
For example, the
famous DART trial
back in the 80s,
involving 2,000 men–
those advised to eat fatty fish
had a 29% reduction in mortality.
Pretty impressive.
No wonder it got a
lot of attention.
But people seem to have
forgotten about the sequel–
the DART II trial.
Same group of
researchers
and even bigger study – 3,000 men.
And those advised
to eat oily fish,
and particularly those supplied
with fish oil capsules
had a HIGHER risk
of cardiac death.
Put all the
studies together...
and there's NO
justification...
for the use of omega-3s as
a structured intervention
in everyday
clinical practice
or for guidelines supporting
more dietary omega-3s.
So what should
doctors say
when their patients follow the
American Heart Association advice
to ask them about
fish oil supplements?
Well, given the new meta-analysis
and other negative meta-analyses,
our job as doctors
should be to STOP
highly marketed fish oil supplementation
in ALL of our patients.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.